<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Mappa mundi, otherwyse called the compasse, and cyrcuet of the worlde and also the compasse of euery ilande, comprehendyd in the same.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1550</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 17 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06861</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S103742</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99839487</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99839487</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3914</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06861)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3914)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 56:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Mappa mundi, otherwyse called the compasse, and cyrcuet of the worlde and also the compasse of euery ilande, comprehendyd in the same.</title>
                  <author>Arnold, Richard, d. 1521? Chronicle. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Imprinted by me Robert Wyer, dwellynge in S. Martyns parysshe, at the sygne of S. John̄ Euangelyst, besyde the duke of Suffolks places, at charynge Cross,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>c. 1550]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon; date of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Taken from Richard Arnold's "Chronicle", published in 1503 with title: "In this boke is conteyned the names of ye baylifs custo[m]s mairs and sherefs of londo[n]" (STC 782).</note>
                  <note>Signature A3r, last line, ends: "and wonders"; B1r last line ends: "frankforth", and C1r last line reads: "The ile of Cecilia, is aboute VII".</note>
                  <note>Some print faded.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>World maps --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Atlases, British --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Mappa Mundi<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Otherwyſe called the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe / and Cyrcuet of the worlde, and alſo the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe of euery Ilande, comprehendyd in the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
                  <p>Ptholoweus</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustrations">
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
                  </figure>
                  <figure>
                     <figDesc>woodcut</figDesc>
                  </figure>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:2"/>
            <head>Mappa mundi.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE generall Hyſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryes of Rome, and Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nycles, maketh mencion of all Cronycles, of the world. And ſpecially of the .vii. bokes hyſtoriall, that ſe Alpheges of caſtell that was choſen Emperoure for his great wyſdome compyled out of the .vij. bokes all the lyfe of Hercules, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the counſayle of Claudeo Tholomeo that compyled out a C. xxxvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. bokes This Hercules was the ſone of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piter kyng of Sogrece and of Almay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne by the quene of Thebes. Alſo Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toleno that hath breuyed all the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuell ſtoryes of Rome, makyng men<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of the .iiij. powers Emperyall / that ben in the worlde.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>¶ The fyrſte Empyre.</head>
               <p>ANd in y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> partie, that is to ſaye in the Eaſt partie, of the wolrd
<pb facs="tcp:3914:3"/> that was the fyrſt Empyre in partia in the tyme of Nynus, and of Gynus and of Serſes and of Sarys, and of Anthyochus, &amp; of many other great kynges reygnyng in the Eaſt partie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>¶ The .ij. Empyre.</head>
               <p>THe ſeconde Empyre, was in the North partie of the world, that is to ſay in Grecia in the tyme of Her<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cules, and of Phelype of Meſſedon, and of Alexandre, &amp; of Pietus kynge of Pirotis, and of many other great kynges reygnynge in Grecia.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>¶ The .iij. Empyre.</head>
               <p>THe thyrde Empyre, was is the Southe, that is to ſaye in Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fryke, in the tyme of Cola kynge of Libia and of Aſe / Rew<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all / and of Amylkare / and of Ancye, &amp; of Amyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kare the yonger, the father of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great Hanyball, and of Aſdrewbal his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb facs="tcp:3914:3"/> and of many great kyngꝭ reyg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyyge in Aufryke.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <head>¶ The .iiii. Empyre.</head>
               <p>THE fourth Empyre, was in the Weſt, that is to ſaye at Rome &amp; of Italye in the tyme of Romulus / that made Rome, and Marco furra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuldo, and of Marco corylyano, and of great Sipion affrecano, &amp; of Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pion humantino, and of great Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la, and of Pompio, and of Iulius Cezer, that was the fyrſte tyraunte and of Octauian, that was the fyrſte crowned Emperour, and of Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyne the ſonne of ſaynt Elyne, and al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſo of many other great kynges in the weſt parte.</p>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Vlius Cezer was one of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>x. worthyes of the worlde, in Armes and Conqueſtes that he made and wonders
<pb facs="tcp:3914:4"/> wyſe in all thynges. That tyme vſed he in his tyme to enſerche and meſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re the worlde in length and bredth, &amp; dyd make therof great Bokes, of all the partyes, countres, and prouinces and wonders in them conteyned, and that bokes accorded to Batylmewe and to Marcus paulus, and to Clau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dius Tholomeus, and to the great Aryſtotle that went w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> kynge Ston<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge, and ben proued true, by many dyuers reaſonable prouynges, but I haue neyther luſt nor leyſure to copye all the bokes, but of all the ſubſtau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that melyked beſt to lerne, &amp; to know for to make ſhortely mencyon, of all the parties of the worlde, as I vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande after myne Auctours, that the worlde is rounde aboute, by the Occian ſee xxiiii. M. myles of aſſyſe of Rome, and .viii. M. myles thwart ouer, and .iiii. M. myles to the mydle there Ieruſalem ſtandeth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and there
<pb facs="tcp:3914:4"/> départeth the worlde in .iiii. parties, Eaſt, weſt, Northe, and Southe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="East" type="part">
               <head>¶ The Eaſt quarter.</head>
               <p>THe fyrſt partye of the worlde, is to vnderſtand from the North to the Southeeſt, all aboute by the coaſtes of the Occian ſee, by the Eaſt partye, and theſe be the names and prouynces of the Eaſt, quarter of the worlde. Ynde maior, Ynde medyan, and the moſte partie of Ynde mynor, and Sanre corneto, Ethyopia, Azo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Greeis, Aponia, Meſapotama, Sacas, Cofides, Mede the moore. Amaſona, Albonia, &amp; a great partie of Percia, the countre of Babell.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="South" type="part">
               <head>¶ The South quarter.</head>
               <p>THe South quarter of the world is from the Southeeſt, to the Southweſt, by the coaſtes of the Oc<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cian ſee, on the ſouth party, and theſe
<pb facs="tcp:3914:5"/> be the names and prouynces, in the ſouth party of the world. Ynde minor Thert the moſt meruayles, ben of dy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uers ſhape of people, &amp; many great wonders, and it is ſo burnynge hote / that no man may dwell there, for the great heat of the Sonne, and Geno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phyſis, &amp; there ben trees of the ſonne and of the Moone, and Brakmana, Meros, Hebrycos, Gyſonas, Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, Bubogras, there groweth, and in the Ile of Cleophas the people ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue no heedes, &amp; Affricabilia, Babilo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Neubra, Arabia, Ethiop, and of Barbary, and parte of Suty.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="West" type="part">
               <head>¶ The Weſtquarter.</head>
               <p>THe weſt quarter of the worlde, is from the Southweſt, to the Northweſt, all aboute the coaſtes of the Occian ſee, in the weſt party, and theſe ben the names and prouynces of the weſt partye of the worlde, and
<pb facs="tcp:3914:5"/> the Maremedian: that ſome men cal the Grekes ſee, &amp; that is in the Weſt quarter of the worlde a parte of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re maior, that lyeth betwixt Turkye and Tartarye, &amp; there lyeth a great parte of Barbary, &amp; of Belmere that is be Southe the ſtreytes Iebaker, and by Northe the ſtreytes Iebal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e theſe ben the prouynces. Fyrſt Hiſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nia that is the Realme of Caſtell, &amp; Lyons<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Dragone, Cataline, Garnat Portugale, Algarne, Galis, Byſhay and Nauerne, and Gallia, is to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtande Fraunce, Guy a prouynce, amorous, Bretayn, Normandy, Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cardy, Turrayne, Lorayne, Buorgon Sauoy, Almayne, that is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, al the honour of the Emperour from the Occian See; to the mounte Gogarde on both the parties of the water of Rygne. The Cyties of the Emperour aforeſayd ben theſe, Acon Col<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yne, Mens, Tryre, Frankforth,
<pb facs="tcp:3914:6"/> Straeſbroth, Baſell, and Conſtans. And ſo forth to the Mountaynes of Almayne, &amp; Bayer, Sweuen, Oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryche, Denmarke, Boeme, Norway, Swecia, Pomar, Pruce, Saxon, Freeſlande, Hollande, Gelderlande, Brabaunte, Flaunders, Englande, Wales, Scotlande, Ireland, and the out Iles of Orbenay, Gutlande, Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Iſelande, Freeſland, and many other ſmal Ilandes, that be i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tie of other the Occian ſee, and Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia is to vnderſtand Pymonde, Lum<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bardy, Froyll, &amp; the Markes of Tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſane, Romayne, Tuſkane de patri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mone of Rome. The duke of Splate the marke of Acon, the realme of Na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples, and Poyle, Taranter, Calabre, the Ile of Serle, and the Ile of Sar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyn, and Grecia, is to vnderſtande, Romenay, Tracia, Teſſalia, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas, Sallydon, Thobas, Aquaya, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> nowe is called, the pryncypalytie of
<pb facs="tcp:3914:6"/> Murre Abania, &amp; all the Ile of the Archpelago, the Ile of Sipre, Rodes Grece, that nowe is called Candye, Corſu, Chiffolonia, Iacento, Nigre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounte, Lango, Calanio, Palamoſe, Niporey, Ixeo, Metholome, Andre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtalau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>to, and many other Iles with in the Archepelago, that is the Gulfe betwyxt Grece and Turkye, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth from the Grekes ſee, into the great ſee before Conſtantynople, tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row the brace of ſ. George. And theſe be the names and prouinces betwixt Grece and the Occian ſee. Towarde the Northweſt parte, that is to ſaye, Hungarye, Polonye, Ruſſe, Ramye, Gallaci, Ludwary, Comney, Blylga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry, Blagy, Cerny, Slawony, &amp; parte of Turkye, and parte of Surry, and the weſt parte of the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="North" type="part">
               <head>¶ The North quarter.</head>
               <pb facs="tcp:3914:7"/>
               <p>THe North quarter of the worlde is for to vnderſtande, from the North weſt to the Northeeſt, by the Occian See, on the Northe partie, and theſe be the names and prouyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the North quarter of the world a parte of Ruſſe lectony, Tartarye, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rty the leſſe, Media, Ermenia the more, there ſtandeth yet the Arke of Noe vpon the Mount of Aracke, and Germynia the leſſe, that goth to the Grekes ſee, in the Northe quarter of the world, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the moſte parte of Turky is in, that is to ſay the realme of Fry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gye, there the great Cytie of Troye ſtandeth, &amp; the realme of Lydia, and Pompſilia, Cilica pounto, there now dwelleth the Emperoure of Trapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande that is a Greke, &amp; king George ſanaſtopoly, that is a chryſten man / and holdeth of the Byſſhop of Rome and his landes ioyneth to Tartarie on the one ſyde, and with the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb facs="tcp:3914:7"/> of Trapaſand on the other ſyde at the Eaſt ende of the Grekes ſee.</p>
               <p>And alſo in the North quarter is in Aſary aliſmace, and a great parte of Surre / there was Anthyoche the great Cytie, there the prynce of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyoche dwelled.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>And alſo the compaſſe of Englan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de rounde aboute is .iiij. thouſande .iii. C. and .lx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ Venys ſtandeth from Flaunders. Eaſt and be ſouth. viij .C. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ And nexte courſe by the ſee, from Flaunders vnto Iaffe is this, from Sluſe to Calys is .lxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Calys to Bewchef .lxxx. my.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Bewchef to Lezarde .ij. hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and .lx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Lezarde to Capefeneſter .vi. hondreth. and .l. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Capefeneſter to Lyſbone .ii. hondreth .lxxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Lyſbone to Cap ſ. Vyncent
<pb facs="tcp:3914:8"/> to the ſtractes .ii. c. xl. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From ſtractes of Iebalter to the Ile of Sardyn .xi. c. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Malfitana in ſardyn to In<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>alta .iiii. c. and .lx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Inalta by the courſe of Sa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rogogora, and Syſyl to ſayle to Iaf in Surry, is. M .viii. c. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Iaf to Baffa in ſypre to the caſtell Roge .ii. c. xx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From the Caſtell Roge to Rodes, is an hondreth myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Rodes to Candy .ii. c. l. my.</item>
                  <item>¶From Candy to Modon .iii. c. my.</item>
                  <item>¶From Modon to corſu .iii. c. myles</item>
                  <item>¶From Corſu to Venis .vii. c. myles</item>
                  <item>☞The length of the coaſtes of Sur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re by the ſet coaſtes, is from the Gulfe of Ermonye: to the Gulfe Dalaryſe nexte the ſouth, and be Weſt, from Lazarye to Ryſe is .v. c. and .xx. myles.</item>
                  <item>☞That is to vnderſtande from La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zary
<pb facs="tcp:3914:8"/> in Ermony to Soldyne, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from the Ryuer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mynge from Anthyoche .lxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶And from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oldyne to the porte of Lycha next to the ſouth .l. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Lytha to the porte of Torto<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſa ſouth .l. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Tortoſa to the porte Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poll. ſouth .l. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Bernet to Acres ſouth and be Weſt .lxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Acres to porte Iaf, South and be weſt .lxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From porte Iaf / to porte Delaza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra ſouth ſouthweſt .c. xxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Damiat Lariza in ſurre, to damiat in Egypt .c. lxxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Damiat / to Babylon Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaer .lxxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶From Damyat, to Alexandre, is. a hondred and .l. myles.</item>
                  <item>☞The length of Mare maior, is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Gulfe ſ. George in myddes of
<pb facs="tcp:3914:9"/> the gulfe that is betwyxt Trapa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſande ſanaſtopoly / vnto the porte of Meſſembre Weſt from ſ. Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge a thouſande .lx. myles.</item>
                  <item>☞ The bredth of the weſtende, is fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the braſe ſ. George at Conſtanty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople / vpon the Ryuer of Dana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bes, next the North, from ſ. Geor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge braſe is .v. c. lx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Pero to Caffa in Tartary Northeeſt .vi. c. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Caffa to the ſtractes of the Tane Northeeſt .c. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The gulfe of the Tane, is aboute .vi. hondred. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The capte of Caffa is aboute .vi. hondred myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From the hed of the Tana to Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtopoly .iiii. c. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Sanaſtopoly to Trapaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de and by weſt .ii. c. l. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Trapaſond to ſynopia, next the ſouth .iiii. c. xxx. myles.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3914:9"/>
                  <item>¶ From Synopia to Pero next the weſt and ſouthweſt .ii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. xxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Pero to Meſſembre next the worthweſt .ii. c xxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Meſſembre to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cro north Northeeſt iii .clx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Mancro caſtro to Danobia Northeeſt .c. xxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ From Danobia to the ſtractes of Caffa next the Eaſt .ii. c. myles.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>¶ The Compaſſe of the Ilandes.</head>
                  <item>THe Ile of Sypre, is aboute .v. hondred myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Rodes, is aboute an hondred .lxxx. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Lange, is aboute .iiij. ſcore myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Nigrepount, is aboute iij. hondred myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Cecilia, is aboute .vii.
<pb facs="tcp:3914:10"/> hondred myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Sardyn, is about .vii. hondred myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Mayorke, is aboute .ii. hondred myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of great Brytayne, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute .ii. M. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The Ile of Irlande, is aboute a. M .vii. c. myles.</item>
                  <item>¶ The pryncypalytie of Murre is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boute .vii. c. myles.</item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <trailer>¶ Thus endeth the length, bredth and compaſſe of the worl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de. And foloweth howe the worlde is deuyded in thre partes. (?)</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:10"/>
            <head>¶ Here foloweth howe the worlde is deuyded in thre partes.</head>
            <p>AL the earth in the world ſhalbe enhabyted, and ſhalbe deuyded in thre partes. The fyrſt partie is na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med Aſſye the great: and is as great as the other two, and this partie du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth from Septemtrion by Oryent tyll myddy. The ſeconde parte is na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Ewrape, and dureth from Occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent vnto Septemtrion. The thyrde partie is named Aufrike that dureth from myddy vnto Occident.</p>
            <p>☞ And Paradyſe terreſter is in the fyrſte regylyon of Aſſye legrande to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde Orient, and there is no earth<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly man that may come there, but god or his angles lede him and gyde him thyther. For this Paradyſe ſythen y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:3914:11"/> Adam was caſt and dryuen out ther of by an Aungell, anone forthwith it was enuironed al aboute with great fyre, that dureth from the erth vnto the ſkye aboue, that no man may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre nor come therto. And there is all about Paradyſe great wylderneſſes where there is alſo great multytude of many dyuers &amp; peryllous beeſtes.</p>
            <p>☞ And alſo hell is in the myddes of Affryke vnder the earth, and is ſet in the myddes of the erth, as a karnell of an apple is in the myddes of the apple, for aſmoch earth is there abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue as beneth. And there be the ſoules that be dampned in great payne and turment with out ende.</p>
            <p>☞ And alſo a man may ſe openly the waters co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth from Paradyſe re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſtre, for there is a wel ſpryng of the whiche .iij. Ryuers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth out of it.
<pb facs="tcp:3914:11"/> And one of tho .iij. Ryuers goeth by the partyes of myddy towarde Ory<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and falleth into the ſee of Occy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and that aryſeth out of an hyll againe that is in the parties of Ynde And the other two Ryuers aryſeth a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gayne i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Ewrope of an hyll and there paſſe by many countres, tyll they me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te, and then they fall in to the ſee as nature requyreth. And alſo a man may ſe in Affryke openlye two hylles that be ſoup<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rall of hell, and they ceaſe not neyther daye nor nyght &amp; be euer bre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nyg with fiers fyre.</p>
            <trailer>¶ Explicit. ¶</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:12"/>
         </div>
         <trailer> ¶ Thus endeth this Mappa mundi Very neceſſary for all Marchauntes, and Mary<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And for all ſuch, as wyll labour &amp; trauey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le in the countres of the worlde. (?)</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <head>¶ Imprinted by me ¶ Robert wyer, dwellynge in ſ. Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyns paryſſhe, at the ſygne of S. Iohu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Euangelyſt, beſyde the Duke of Suff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lkes places, at tharynge Croſſe.</head>
            <p>¶ Cum priuilegio, ad impri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendum ſofum.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="astrological_diagrams">
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:12"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut astrological diagrams</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:13"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>Robert Wyer's device</figDesc>
                  <p>ROBERT WYER.</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:3914:13"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
